Tucson Poetry Festival Records, circa 1982-2004
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Tucson Poetry Festival Records 1984-2004
MS 510
Tucson Poetry Festival
Records, 1982-2004. This collection contains materials relating to the Tucson Poetry Festival, an annual festival dedicated to promoting poetry as a medium for artistic expression. The collection is comprised primarily of correspondence with poets and the administrative materials pertaining to Tucson Poetry Festival coordination, such as grant writing. Newspapers and festival ephemera(TPF programs, flyers, and posters) are also included.
6 Linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
The Tucson Poetry Festival(TPF) is one of the oldest poetry festivals in the United States. The TPF has been part of the Tucson creative writing landscape since its inception in 1981 by founding president, John Hudak. However, the first Tucson Poetry Festival was held in 1983. TPF has exposed renowned poets to Tucson for over 30 years and is still in existence. Some of the most renowned poets include: Allen Ginsberg, Joy Harjo, Simon Ortiz, W.S. Merwin, Yusef Komunyakaa, Sherman Alexie, Diane di Prima, Wanda Coleman, N. Scott Momaday, Gary Snyder, and many more greats.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 7 series
Series I- Administration 1983-2002
Series II- Poets 1983-2002
Series III- Contests 1992-2003
Series IV- Grants 1982-2002
Series V- Newspapers 1983-2002
Series VI- Ephemera 1983-2004
Series VII- T-Shirts
Scope and Content Note
This collection spans the entirety of the Tucson Poetry Festival’s existence from 1982-2004. The bulk of the collection is administrative materials pertaining to TPF committee coordination. Administrative materials include committee minutes and agendas, poet-organization correspondence, and grant applications. Newspapers and ephemera such as TPF posters, flyers, and program trifolds are also included. Users will be able to investigate the relationship with poets and the organizational structure that the TPF has constructed throughout their history as a venue for artistic expression.
Access Terms
Poetry -- Collections
Arts -- Arizona
Poets, American -- 20th Century
American poetry -- 20th Century; >
Nonprofit organizations -- Arizona
Nonprofit organizations -- Management
Correspondence
Container List
- Series I- Administrative 1983-2002
  Series is sorted by year. This series contains committee minutes and agendas, handwritten notes, handwritten media revisions, reference materials, volunteer information, venue agreements, contracted services, organization synopsis, treasury reports, donations, memorandums, preparatory notes on TPF programs, and correspondence. Correspondence is between the TPF, the public, and business partnerships.
  - Administrative, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adminstrative, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Administrative, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adminstrative, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrative, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administrative, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Administrative, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administrative, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Administrative, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Administrative, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Administrative, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Administrative, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Administrative, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II- Poets 1983-2002
  Series is sorted by year of annual poetry festival. Within each year, each poet is alphabetically arranged by surname. Poets were invited and participated, declined, or construed as prospects. Series contains correspondence between poets and TPF, biographies, profile pictures, and sample poetry produced by poets.
  - Ignatow, David, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rios, Alberto, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Inman, Will, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Anderson, Barbara, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carrol, Christopher, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dove, Rita, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ingalls, Jeremy, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Johnson, Denis, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Momaday, N. Scott, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pape, Greg, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rivera, Marina, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Smith, Ken, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Territory Dance Theatre, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Levertov, Denise, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lykes, Dorothy, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ortiz, Simon, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Dark Bob, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Wakoski, Diane, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - McCarthy, Eugene, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Rios, Alberto, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bersenbrugge, Mei-Mei, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Nichol, b.p., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Silliman, Ron, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Tarn, Nathaniel, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Davis, Meg, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Marlatt, Daphne, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miller, Jane, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rose, Wendy, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Silliman, Ron, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tarn, Nathaniel, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Baraka, Amiri, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Harjo, Joy, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hogue, Cynthia, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Taylor, Cecil, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ali, Agha Shahid, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Anderson, Barbara, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bakken, Dick, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Berry, Wendell, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bly, Robert, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clifton, Lucille, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dove, Rita, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Gallagher, Tess, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Ignatow, David, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Merwin, William, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Palmer, Michael, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ali, Agha Shahid, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Bly, Robert, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Forche, Carolyn, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Mitchell, Stephen, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Noll, Bruce, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Rios, Alberto, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Rothenberg, Jerome, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Waldrup, Rosemarie, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Zepeda, Ofelia, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Angelou, Maya, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Anzaldua, Gloria, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Cisneros, Sandra, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Di Prima, Diana, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Howe, Susan, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Komunyakaa, Yosef, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Mackey, Nathaniel, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Martinez, Demetria, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Milosz, Czeslaw, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Penn, Barbara, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Silko, Leslie, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Walcott, Derek, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Alarcon, Francisco X., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Amichai, Yehuda, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Baker, David, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Campo, Rafael, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Di Prima, Diane, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Hacker, Marilyn, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jordan, June, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miller, Jane, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Olds, Sharon, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rickel, Boyer, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ai, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ali, Agha Shahid, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Alexie, Sherman, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bidart, Frank, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Boland, Eavan, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Deming, Allison, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Saenz, Benjamin, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cully, Barbara, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Davis, Jon, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Doty, Mark, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Hejinian, Lyn, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Howe, Mary, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Kizer, Carolyn, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Noguchi, Rick, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Simic, Charles, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Woody, Elizabeth, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Zamara, Daisy, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Baca, Jimmy, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Byrkit, Becky, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Chin, Marilyn, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Deming, Alison, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Hongo, Garret, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Macdonald, Cynthia, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Moss, Thylias, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Simic, Charles, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Amichai, Yehuda, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Bernstein, Charles, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Bly, Robert, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Brooks, Jeffrey, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Espada, Martin, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Gluck, Louise, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Hirshfield, Jane, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Hunter, Robert, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Lomatewama, Ramson, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Mora, Pat, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Moss, Thylias, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Olds, Sharon, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Oliver, Mary, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Rich, Adrienne, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Root, William Pitt, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Shapiro, David, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Patricia, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Snyder, Gary Sherman, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Woody, Elizabeth, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wright, Charles, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Coleman, Wanda, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Divakaruni, Chitra Banerjee, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Guest, Barbara, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Herrera, Juan Felipe, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Jim, Rex Lee, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Kowit, Steve, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Levine, Philip, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Olds, Sharon, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Mairs, Nancy, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Mirikitani, Janice, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Stern, Gerald, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Sze, Arthur, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Tohe, Laura, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Valentine, Jean, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Wendell, Berry, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Wright, Charles, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Yau, John, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Kumin, Maxine, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Alexander, Charles, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Alexie, Sherman, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Caroll, Andrew, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Glazner, Gary Mex, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Oliver, Mary, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Miller, Jane, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Rios, Alberto, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Snyder, Gary, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Waldman, Anne, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Series III- Contests 1992-2003
  Series contains three different types of contests: Statewide Poetry Contest, Bilingual Poetry Contest, and Pima County Adult Education Poetry Contest. Series is sorted by contest type, then by year within annual contest. These contests run concordantly with the Tucson Poetry Festival. Materials within include correspondence with amateur poets and high school students who submitted poetic works for critique by TPF designated guest judge. Contains bounded collections of poetry as the contest final product.
  - Statewide Poetry Contest, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Statewide Poetry Contest, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Statewide Poetry Contest, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Statewide Poetry Contest, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bilingual Poetry Contest, 1996-2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bilingual Poetry Contest, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pima Adult Education Poetry Contest, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series IV- Grants 1982-2002
  Series is sorted alphabetically by foundation, then by year. Materials contained in series pertain to descriptions of budget, grant proposal, festival history and past participants, foundation ‘how-to’ guides for grant writing criteria, committee member list intended for grant foundational assessment and liaison. There are included some TPF committee- grant foundation correspondence.
  - American Express, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Arizona Commission Arts, 1982-1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Arizona Commission Arts, 1994-200 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Arizona Commission Arts, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Arizona Humanities Council, 1985-1992 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Arizona Humanities Council, 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Citibank, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Community Foundation Southern Arizona, 1999-2002 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - DeGrazia Art Culture Foundation, 1984-1993 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Gannett Foundation, 1984-1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Hudson Webber Foundation, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - J.C. Penney, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Lanna Foundation, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Marshall Fund Arizona, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mervyns, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Mountain Bell, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - National Endowment Arts, 1984-1995 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - National Endowment Arts film grant, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Puffin Foundation, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Stonewall Foundation, 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Tucson Arts District, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Tucson Community Foundation, 1987-1998 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Tucson Partnership Inc., 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Tucson Pima Arts Council, 1985-1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Tucson Pima Arts Council, 1993-1997 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Tucson Pima Arts Council, 1997-2001 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Research Corporation, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - US West Communications, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Western States Arts Festival, 1999-2002 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Witter Bynner Foundation, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Series V- Newspapers 1983-2002
  Series is sorted as types: newspaper clippings and oversize whole papers, then by date of publication. Newspapers primarily range from local press to University press, but national press is included (American Poetry Review, The Daily Wildcat, Tucson Citizen, Tucson Weekly) pertaining to the TPF program as review.
  - Newspapers, Clippings, 1983-1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Newspapers, Clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Newspapers, Clippings, 1994-1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, Clippings, 2000-2002 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Newspapers, Oversize, 1987-2002 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Series VI- Ephemera 1983-2004
  Series is sorted by year. This series contains flyers, posters, TPF program trifolds, ticket stubs that describe TPF main events, poetry contests, and other peripheral events (workshops, open mic). Oversize Posters are from the first anniversary to TPF XXII.
  - Ephemera, 1983-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ephemera, 1990-1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Ephemera, 1999-2000 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera, 2001-2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera, Oversize Posters, 1983-2004 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Series VII- T-Shirts 1983-1993
  Assortment of graphic tees. Annual TPF t-shirts describe TPF poet participants.
  - TPF T-shirt I, 1983 (Box 11)
  - TPF T-shirt II, 1984 (Box 11)
  - TPF T-shirt IV, 1986 (Box 11)
  - TPF T-shirt VI, 1988 (Box 11)
  - TPF T-shirt IX, 1991 (Box 11)
  - TPF T-shirt X, 1992 (Box 11)
  - TPF T-shirt XI, 1993 (Box 11)